<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC7437 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7437.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4071 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4071.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4371 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4371.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5378 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7979 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7979.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hall-iasa2-struct SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hall-iasa2-struct.xml">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-arkko-iasa2-trust-rationale-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="IASA 2.0 and IETF Trust">
      Discussion of the IASA 2.0 Changes as They Relate to the IETF
      Trust</title>
    
    <author fullname="Jari Arkko" initials="J." 
            surname="Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Kauniainen</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>02700</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>

      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date month="June" year="2018" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>The IASA 2.0 changes will have an impact on the IETF Trust
      because members of the IET Administrative Oversight
      Committee (IAOC) IAOC, which is being phased out, have served
      as Trustees of the IETF Trust. This discussion document provides
      background on the current IETF Trust arrangements, explains the effect of
      the rules in the founding documents during a transition to a new
      arrangement, and provides a rationale for the update.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>The IASA 2.0 changes will have an impact on the IETF Trust 
      <xref target="RFC4071"/> <xref target="RFC4371"/> <xref
      target="I-D.hall-iasa2-struct"/>. This is because members of the
      IETF's Internet Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC), which 
      is being phased out, have served as Trustees of the IETF Trust. 
      A proposal for a minimal change regarding this has been provided 
      separately in draft-arkko-iasa2-trust-update.</t>
      
      <t>This companion memo provides some background on the details
      of the current IETF Trust arrangements, explains the effect of
      the rules in the founding documents during a transition to a new
      arrangement, and provides a rationale for the update.</t>

      <t>This memo is provided only for discussion. There is no
      intention to publish this memo as an RFC.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="background" title="Background">
      
      <t>The purpose of the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) Trust 
      is to acquire, hold, maintain,
      and license certain existing and future intellectual property
      and other property used in connection with the administration of
      the IETF <xref target="RFC4371"/>. The intellectual property is,
      for instance, rights that the IETF contributors grant for text
      in RFCs and Internet Drafts. The IETF Trust also manages
      trademarks such as "IETF" and domain names such as "ietf.org". The IETF
      Trust is also serving the broader Internet community by holding
      domains and trademarks associated with Internet Assigned Numbers 
      Authority (IANA) <xref target="RFC7979"/>.</t>
      
      <t>The IETF Trust is a legal entity, registered in the
      Commonwealth of Virginia <xref target="Trust-FD"/>.</t>
      
      <t>Currently, the members of the IAOC also serve as ex officio
      Trustees of the IETF Trust. The founding documents specify
      persons eligible to become trustees as having to be then-current
      members of the IAOC <xref target="Trust-FD"/>.  The documents
      also specify that if for any reason there are fewer than three
      individuals serving as Trustees, then the Internet Engineering 
      Steering Group (IESG), or the IESG's successor as the leadership 
      of the IETF, shall appoint one or more individuals to serve in a 
      temporary capacity as Trustee(s) until eligible persons can be found.</t>
      
      <t>In the current system there are eight IAOC members. Two are
      named by the IETF Nominating Committee (NomCom), one by the
      IESG, one by the Internet Architecture Board (IAB), and one by 
      the Internet Society (ISOC) Board of Trustees. In addition, there 
      are three ex-officio members via their roles as IETF Chair, ISOC CEO, 
      and IAB Chair. In addition, the IETF Administrative Director (IAD)
      serves also as one of the trustees.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="approach" title="General Approach">
      
      <t>There are two basic approaches to resolving the issue with
      the trustees, if the IAOC ceases to exist.  One could imagine
      merging all IETF Trust functions in the new IASA structure and
      under the planned new legal entity. This memo advocates a second
      approach where the IETF Trust is kept independent.</t>
      
      <t>The rationale for advocating the second approach is in part
      to minimize changes to the IETF Trust while the IETF's 
      administrative structure is undergoing major change.
      In addition, the IETF Trust and other administrative IETF process 
      are quite different. While very important, the IETF Trust is a low 
      activity entity where changes are minimal and gradual, and there are no pressing
      issues.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="selection" title="Changing the Way Trustees Are Selected">
      
      <t>At the time when the trustees served on both the IETF Trust and the
      IAOC, many of the requirements for naming a particular group of
      people were driven by the IAOC's requirements.  For the IETF
      Trust in the new model, some of those arrangements can be
      rethought, both in terms of the number and source of the
      trustees, as well as the desired qualifications and length of
      terms.</t>
      
      <t>Several options are possible, of course. A newly designed
      naming process could be devised. This memo argues for relatively
      limited change, however, largely on the basis of the IETF Trust
      arrangements generally working well, and on the relatively modest
      expected time commitments combined with the need for very careful
      management of the assets.</t>
      
      <t>As a result, a smaller group of trustees appears sufficient.</t>
      
      <t>In addition, the terms for the
      trustees selected from the IETF community could be set to longer than
      the two year period typical of other IETF bodies.</t>
      
      <t>One could continue the practice of having the chairs and CEOs
      from IETF, IAB, and Internet Society be trustees as well, but
      this may not be necessary. In general, the tasks of the IETF
      Trust are well defined, and while there is a need for
      coordination, it does not need to be at the level of chairs or
      CEOs.</t>

      <t>Given all this, one approach is to have
      trustees appointed by the NomCom, IESG, and
      ISOC Board of Trustees, or even the new IETF Administration LLC 
      legal entity (but he Internet Society is perhaps more focused on 
      the broad use of the IETF Trust assets and not merely administrative
      aspects).</t>
      
      <t>If the same principles continue to be used as are used in
      today's appointments, then appointments performed by the
      NomCom need to be confirmed by another entity,
      which could be, for instance, either the IESG or the IAB.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="transition" title="Transition">

      <t>When new entity for IETF Administration LLC is set
      up, soon thereafter the IAOC will be discontinued. Fortunately,
      there's no pressing need to change all the components at the
      same time. As discussed above (<xref target="background"/>), the
      IESG holds the ability to continue to name trustees. Once the
      changes suggested in <xref target="selection"/> are in place, the
      IETF Trust will have management nominated in the usual manner,
      and the exceptional IESG process is no longer needed.</t>

    </section>
    
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      
      <t>The author would like to thank members of the earlier IASA
      2.0 design team, as well as Alissa Cooper, Ted Hardie, Andrew
      Sullivan, Brian Carpenter, Lucy Lynch, and John Levine for
      interesting discussions in this problem space.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC4071;
      &RFC4371;
      &RFC7437;
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC5378;
      &RFC7979;
      &I-D.hall-iasa2-struct;
      
      <reference anchor='I-D.arkko-iasa2-trust-update'>
	<front>
	  <title>Update to the Selection of Trustees for the IETF Trust</title>

	  <author initials='J' surname='Arkko' fullname='Jari Arkko'>
	    <organization />
	  </author>

	  <author initials='T' surname='Hardie' fullname='Ted Hardie'>
	    <organization />
	  </author>

	  <date month='June' year='2018' />

	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-arkko-iasa2-trust-update-00' />
	<format type='TXT'
		target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-arkko-iasa2-trust-update-00.txt' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="Trust-FD">
        <front>
          <title>Founding Documents</title>
          <author surname="IETF Trust"></author>
	  <date month='February' year='2014 (https://trustee.ietf.org/founding-documents.html)'/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
		target='https://trustee.ietf.org/founding-documents.html'/>
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
